So this video is going
to talk a little bit
about what to expect
for our upcoming lab,
area of greatest
restriction, and
facility position
release of the spine.
So we're going to talk about
approaching our patient
to try to find the area of
greatest restriction. We're
going to demonstrate and
perform this screening on
your partners, and then talk
about how utilizing this
sequencing will help to
improve your ability to manage
your patients and formulate
a treatment approach.
I'm going to talk a little
bit about the use of
facilitated positional
release to treat patients'
somatic dysfunctions,
and we're going to apply
it to the cervical,
thoracic and lumbar regions.
So as a student, I was
exposed to this concept of
tensegrity in manual therapy,
and it really kind of opened
up the different options
and how we look at the body.
We're not blocks on top
of each other, kind of
compressed on each other,
but actually we're more of
a tensegritous structure,
And tensegrity is initially
more of an architectural
concept where we have
these rods that are held
up by these wires, which
kind of hold this tension
around the structure and
keeps it upright. And so
our body is similar with
our bones being those
rods and these wires
supporting, which is the
fascia, muscle, and ligaments.
And so when we move one
area, it affects the tension
in the other area. And so
if you ever had like this
kind of toy ball, if you kind
of compressed in one area,
then the whole system kind
of tightens up. And so
this sort of approach really
kind of makes you think
about whole person. If I
have tension in one area, how
could that tension affect
the entire body? And so Dr.
Edward Stiles presented
this at convocation, one of
the conferences that I
attended as a student, and he
continues to do so. And he
kind of talks about how he
developed this concept and
approaches his patients.
The other thing Dr. Stiles
talked about was Dr.
Ingber's paper. So this was
Dr. Ingber, he was an MD,
PhD out of Harvard, and
he produced a paper back
in 2003. And the paper
talks about mechanobiology
and the diseases of
mechanotransduction and how a lot
of the different processes
that go on in our body
on even a cellular level
really depends on mechanical
forces. And so this being
written by an allopathic
physician really had
significant impact upon
how we look at the body,
because as osteopathic
physicians, we're always
looking at how mechanical forces
is affecting our health
and system. And so in
his paper, he describes many
different concepts where
mechanical transduction
could affect our health.
So one of the things
that he stresses is how
all our cells have
deep anchors into the
extracellular matrix.
and movement of the
extracellular matrix
helps to trigger different
signals that causes a
change in gene expression.
And so it kind of makes
sense. Our cells know
that if there's a lot of
space to grow, that then
they'll grow. But if it
gets really crowded and
there's a lot of different
cells kind of crowding
it, then it has to
undergo shape change and
apoptosis. And so So
these physical forces on
cells will dictate what
happens to those cells.
So in his paper,
he talks about how
these mechanical
forces are critical
regulators of
cellular biochemistry.
So there's an undeniable
physical basis of disease.
What happens if the cell,
when it's crowded, does
not express the right genes
to undergo apoptosis? So
then you have a cancer
cell, right? cells that are
dividing uncontrollably and
not dying off. So there's
a lot of different forces
that are applied to an
entire organism, whether
it be gravity or movement,
that could be distributed
to the individual cells
via these adhesions into
the extracellular matrix.
In addition, he gives
a lot of other examples
of how these forces
affect different aspects.
the shapes of the cells
dictate this behavior these
are mediated through
tension changes through the
cytoskeletal structure the
extracellular matrix a lot of
manual therapies have
therapeutic value because they
alter that mechanotransduction
and a lot of the clinical
problems that bring patients
to the doctor's office
results from these tissue
structures and mechanics
So really,
ultimately, his paper says,
consequently, it would be
wise to look for a physical
cause for disease, which
kind of branches off from
the persistent discussion
to, you know, you have a
problem, take a medicine to
change it, right? Here is a
paper that says, hey, on a
cellular level, there's a
lot of things that happen
in terms of mechanical forces
on the cell, which affects
how the cell functions,
which then dictates behavior
and health. And so here is
a totally different lens
as to why we should be
looking at our patients to
treat them with manual forces
and manual manipulation.
Some additional examples of
effects of manual effects
on human body, increased
bone formation versus
cartilage when we do
mechanical loading. So that's
really important with
osteoporosis, and that's something
that we know. So patients
that have bone loss, we
want to increase bone
formation by telling them to
load and do weight-bearing
exercises, right? Increase
skeletal mass to stretch,
that we know too. If you
go to the gym and you
work out a muscle over and
over, that muscle is going
to increase the mass because
it's increasing due to
the stretch on the muscle.
patients that go into
heart failure this
is something that they
detect they look for
the hormone that's secreted
by the atria secondary
to stretch and so that's
something actually if
someone has heart failure
they will check the blood
and look for and detect
those levels in fact that's
now a treatment and they
give BMP to patients with
heart failure stretching
of the Lung tissue
regulates synthesis of
different extracellular matrix.
If you have microgravity,
it causes different
atrophies to the heart,
bone, and muscles.
Relate to aging.
Blood flow is influenced
by the forces surrounding
it. In fact, they study
this frequently in the
hearts. If they put in
a mechanical valve, what
happens to the flow and
how should they attach it?
So again, structure and
function, how that interacts.
Increase in growth in skin,
bone, and fibroblasts
to stretch.
Your kidney, your bladder
cells, your pulmonary
cells change in
growth due to stretch.
Also, there's increased deposit
of bone due to mechanical
stress. So if you
injure somewhere and you
continually move it over and
over, or this is an example
where if you irritate your
plantar fascia, bone is the
strongest element in your
body. So if you frequently
tear that fascia on the
bottom of your foot over and
over and over, it starts to
lay down more and more bone
to try to protect it
because that's the strongest
element in the body. And
now you develop a heel spur.
So these are some examples of
mechanical effects
on the human body.
Forces on the cellular
level is really evident in
embryology. How do our cells
know how to differentiate
to become certain cells,
right? So this was studied
by Dr. Bleschmidt, and
they looked at how these
biokinetic or movements
created biodynamic or forces
which caused cells to
differentiate from different
layers. And part of it
is whether the cells
are being pushed together
or pulled, it changed
what sort of cell it
would differentiate into.
These forces are evident
when you look at bone,
right? So Dr. Wolf in 1892
observed that bone reshapes
in responses to the forces
acting on it. So if you
look at the dissected
hip bone here, the femur,
you can see how the different
forces on the bone create
this, right? We know
that the mastoid process
on babies don't exist because
it doesn't exist until
they start to lift
up their head and the
sternocleidomastoid starts
to pull on the temporal bone,
creating that mastoid
process, right? So bones will
change based on the pulls
and forces on those bones.
Part of it is because of
this piezoelectric effect.
And so when we load bone, it
polarizes the bone, and so
our osteoblasts and osteoclasts
know where should they
either take calcium from or
lay down more bone, right?
So this mechanical stress
causes an electrical field
around bone, which then
signals to our cells that
take away or build bone where
they should be building.
So we could see that
all the way from the
cellular level, we
could have effects, and
these forces will have
an effect on the cells,
all the way to our
musculoskeletal system.
One key thing that we
look at, especially with
thinking of whole body,
whole person, and how
these forces affect
things, is to look at the
fascia. So the fascia is
what surrounds muscle.
And within the fascia,
there's a lot of different
important structures. And
now we're finding more and
more importance. there's
been several fascial
congresses now pointing out
all the different important
vasculature,
circulation,
lymphatics, nervous system,
key things that are traversing
through the fascial
system which affects pain,
which affects a lot of
different aspects of our health.
So, you can see very
complex, a lot of different
cytokines within their immune
system, connective tissue,
extracellular matrix
proteins, collagen.
And so, when you have
strain in the fascia, that
could create different
responses throughout the body.
So this was an interesting
study published. They took
cells from an asthmatic
versus cells from a non
-asthmatic, and they plated those
cells out, these fibroblast
cells, and they created a
strain on the cells. and
the asthmatics bronchial
fibroblasts secreted more IL
-6 inflammatory mediators
compared to the normal. So
just putting the strain on
the cell showed an increase
in inflammation, which is a
key issue in asthma, right?
And so when someone's an
asthmatic, yes, they take
medications to help
bronchodilate, open up the airway.
They'll take steroids to
try to calm this. But if we
could try to remove some of
this strain on our patients
who are asthmatics could
you potentially decrease
that inflammatory process also
there has been correlations
to the thickness of fascia
with aging and flexibility
and pain chronic pain and
so this was done looking
at using ultrasound to look
at the thickness of the
fascia, the deep fascia,
and they found a correlation
that older patients had
thicker fascia and also that
restricted range of motion,
right? And so they're definitely
tied to issues with the
fascia and how that could
cause pain and cause a
decrease in range of motion.
Dr. Thomas Myers wrote a
book about these different
fascial lines, right? Fascia
goes throughout our entire
body and in lab, we're
going to take a look at how
assessing key regions
might result in finding an
area of greatest restriction.
And a lot of times when
we treat that restriction,
other areas will resolve.
And so when you think
about how we're all one
tensegrative structure and
these different fascial lines,
like if I hurt my plantar
fascia on the right side,
it will pull all the way up
to my head, right? And it
could kind of cause issues
with my headache, right?
If I sprain my ankle on the
side here, it could pull
all the way up into the
shoulder. So all these different
fascial connections, yes,
fascia is all kind of
interconnected, but they,
Dr. Myers talked a little
bit about these fascial
lines, which tend to exhibit
these pain patterns a
little bit more frequently.
So we're going to talk
a little bit about this
superficial back line. In
lab, you can see how, again,
like I said, the plantar
fascia connects into
the back of the leg,
into the rectospinae, and
comes all the way here and
touches to your eyebrow.
And so if this line is
tight, it's going to prevent
someone from bending
forward to try to touch
your toes. And so we're
going to talk a little bit
more about treating some
of these key areas and
seeing if it could improve
range of motion in lab.
Here is that connection
again, the superficial back
line written out here and
it kind of comes all the way
up and attaches along that
super overall ridge here.
So how does all
this information
help us as physicians?
We have that hands-on
training to kind of
diagnose and treat
physical dysfunctions that
could influence disease.
Our treatment of the
body is not just the
musculoskeletal system, it
could actually reach
down all the way down to
the cellular level,
which is pretty amazing.
And you could treat a
lot of different diseases
just by thinking about
how you could treat these
dysfunctions, which is
influencing these mechanical
forces on the body and
thus on the cellular level.
so where do we start so
this approach um that we're
going to go over in lab was
developed by dr edward styles
and he um taught it to me
and several other um at
several schools he's been
dean at several schools and a
lot of um a lot of people
tend to use this approach to
help differentiate where
the greatest restriction is
located because it kind of
makes sense if you treat what's
most restricted a lot of
times by treating that one
main problem other areas of
compensation might release
and you might not have to
work as hard right when you
when you want to treat a
patient you kind of want to
start with maybe what's the
most stuck and if you could
treat that area perhaps
they'll get other areas of
compensation to relax and you
may not have to even if that
dysfunction might not even
be there if you really
target and treat the area
that's most restrictive first.
And so utilizing this area
of greatest restriction
approach gives you a
sequence, gives you a starting
place of where to treat,
allows the physician to focus
on the root of the problem
and not just areas of
compensation. And it helps
to keep us, this whole person
in mind when we treat and
not just focus on every
complaint. Because if
someone complains of shoulder
pain, that shoulder pain
actually might be coming from
their lower back or from
their ankle that they
sprain, like we said before.
And so in order to kind of
screen the patient and not
be fixated on just looking
for that one area that
they're complaining about,
keeping this in mind
helps you to kind
of keep this whole
person in mind.
So when we're screening,
we're going to be moving
the spine and the body in
three different planes. And
we're using Friot's principle
to diagnose because when
we move in one plane,
then it limits the motion in
another plane. So actually
when you move in all three
planes, eventually you'll
find a physiological
locking. It kind of makes
sense. If I sit up straight,
I could have full rotation.
But if I now side bend and
then rotate, now I could
move less. And now if I
side bend and flex and then
try to rotate, you could
feel how you're going to
reach a end barrier quicker.
So you're trying to find
this elastic barrier to
find areas of restriction.
And when you have a normal
joint, usually that's
going to feel springy.
It's not going to feel
really restricted and
stuck. But when you hit a
restrictive barrier, there's
going to be an earlier
locking. You're going to
feel a lot more restriction
in the movement arm
and your palpating arm.
And there'll be a gradation
of that dysfunction
with one being kind of
mild, two being moderate,
three being really
severe. That's the most
restricted dysfunction. As
you practice this, you'll
get better and it'll get
easier to distinguish.
So here's Dr. Stiles and he
gave permission for me to
utilize his PowerPoint.
He shared it with me. So a
lot of this is his PowerPoint
and his descriptors. You're
going to start at the neck.
You're going to let your
fingers kind of rest on
both sides of the neck and
your other hands on the head
and you're going to very
gently bring the head
into side bending put in
some flexion or extension
and then add the rotation
as you do that you're
going to again feel from
your motion hand on the
head on top of the head and
your other hand on the
neck and as you move it
you'll feel oh does it
feel really stuck where my
thumb is? Does it feel
more stuck where my fingers
are? Does it feel hard
to move the head back
into my fingers? There's
also a link for the video
of him describing this.
I suggest you watch it.
It's very informative
and it gives it firsthand
from the person who
kind of came up with
this approach.
So if it's soft and springs,
that's normal. If it's
hard and doesn't spring,
then that's abnormal. We're
going to move down into
the thoracic spine and
here we're going to put one
hand over the shoulder and
then slowly move our
hand down from the upper,
middle, lower thoracic region,
right? And again, we're
using Frey's principle
number three. We're going
to add a sweeping motion,
starting with a little bit
of side bending and then
flexion and then rotation
and then side
bending and extension
and then rotation,
right? And again,
slow motions, sweeping
motions, and you'll be able
to feel a restriction in
your monitoring hand on the
back and also as you're
moving the shoulder back.
Dr. Stiles did perform this
examination, sitting and
standing. If the key restriction
is sacral when you're
sitting, then it's probably
the SI joint. If it's
standing, it's probably a
gait or anonimate dysfunction.
So here's the image.
Again, he does a sweeping
motion slow deliberate
upper thoracic mid
thoracic and then lower
thoracic and then you can
repeat this over the
lumbar and SI regions.
So once you've done this
sweeping right you start to
you've graded you know one
two or three you kind of
go back and say hey you
know three was the most
severe in the lower cervical
if it's really upper
cervicals then that might be
something going on in cranial,
if it's middle or lower
cervicals, then you go
and check the cervical segments
that are most restricted
and you treat it with
your treatment of choice,
right? It could be FPR, it
could be muscle energy, it
could be soft tissue, it
could be HPA, whatever BLT,
whatever treatment of approach
that's indicated for that
patient. Once you find a
global or general area, then
you have to find a segmental
restriction in that
area, treat it and go back
and re-screen the whole body.
If I find something in
the thoracic region,
I want to palpate laterally
at that region. So
if it was upper thoracics
and I palpate out
laterally and it feels
like, hey, it feels like
it's kind of getting better
as I palpate laterally,
then that might be
more of a thoracic
dysfunction. So then I
go ahead and screen that
thoracic dysfunction in
that region and treat it.
But if I palpate out laterally,
it doesn't have to be
here, but wherever I felt
the area of restriction, as
I palpate out laterally
and it feels more stuck, it
feels worse, then it might
be a rib cage problem. If it
is a rib cage problem, it
doesn't mean to treat that
rib. If you have a rib
cage problem, you have to
rescreen the entire rib cage
because remember, when we have
a rib problem, sometimes
it's not that one rib you're
feeling, but it could be a
rib in that whole general
group that's the problem.
So then you have to treat
the key rib. So you have
to find that key rib, find
the key group first. So
re-screen the entire rib
cage. It might end up
being on the opposite side
from where you found that
restriction. That's okay.
By finding something that's
more restricted
as you come out,
go ahead and screen the
entire rib cage. And then
remember when you're
looking for that key rib,
remember the key rib of a
group of inhaled rib is the
bottom rib and a key rib of
the group of exhaled ribs
is the top rib because
that top rib prevents all
the other ribs from moving
up on inhalation, right?
So identify the key group
and the key rib, and
then treat that rib, and
then re-screen. Sometimes
you'll be surprised. It
might be a rib on the other
side, and all of a sudden,
the area that you were
feeling that was most
restricted is much improved.
If I find a band-like restriction
medial to the scapula.
A lot of times that might
point towards an upper
extremity key dysfunction,
right? What do we do when we
have issues with our shoulder,
elbows, or wrists is we
tend to kind of brace and
engage our rhomboid muscles
and our upper back muscles
as we reach to compensate
for that lack of mobility
or pain. And so if you find
this band-like restriction
on one side, it's important
to screen the upper extremity,
including the clavicular,
sternoclavicular and
acromioclavicular joints
because our clavicle is the
main strut that holds our upper
extremity, right? So don't
forget to screen at the
clavicle, check your radial
head, check the wrist and
hand, check the shoulder,
right? You could do the upper
extremity kind of general
screen. They do that and
check specifically for
shoulder, elbow, wrist issues.
And a lot of times if I
feel this and then I ask the
patient, hey, have you been
having pain in your wrist or
your elbow? And they'll be
like, yeah, I had. I just
totally forgot to tell you
about it. So a lot of times,
trust what you're sensing
and palpating in your
patient. Don't go by just what
they're complaining about.
When we want to screen
the lower half of
the body, we're going
to perform a standing
forward bend test or
standing flexion test and
also a sitting forward
bend test, right? Both of
these will evaluate the
sacrum and the inanimate,
but we're going to look
now if our standing
flexion or a seated
flexion, they could both be
positive, but which one
was more positive, meaning
which one was more severe
with your finger on the
PSIS going further
compared to the other side.
If I find a unilateral
pattern in the lumbar spine,
just like with upper
extremity, we've got to
think lower extremity. Maybe
something's going on with
that ipsilateral leg.
Maybe there's something
going on with the hip,
knees, ankle. So definitely
double check. If you find
something really tight
along one side, right,
that might be a issue with
the lower extremity. If I
find just like a key region
in the lumbar, maybe
it's a segmental issue in
the lumbar spine, but if
I find a paravertebral
restriction along that
lumbar spine, it's something
that I have to screen now
the lower extremity for.
So this approach, area
regressor restriction, is to
try to find that key
restriction. Sometimes it might
be totally located in a
different area of the body,
right?
Pain usually is where the
body's trying to compensate.
It may not necessarily
be the area of greatest
restriction. So here
when we're screening for
the area of greatest
restriction, really trust what
you're palpating and
what you're sensing with
your hands and treating
that and then reassessing,
right? So the sequence is
once you find that regional
restriction, establish
a segmental restriction
area, treat it, and then
rescreen just like how you
started, right? Then you
move on to the next regional
area of grace restriction,
and you treat that area,
right? And Stiles would
treat like one, two, or three
areas, and then he would
be done for the visit,
because he would say that
once you like reach like the
fourth or fifth thing,
that's not really changed,
or usually one or two or
three things, once you get
those things released, the
other dysfunctions don't
feel even present anymore,
right? So you'll find that
the areas that you graded
as mild might be resolved
after treating that area
for your subscription just
because of that tensegritous
concept that everything's
kind of interconnected,
right? We have this
allostatic load that if
we're tight in the fascia in
one area, once we release
that one key area, perhaps
things are moving better
throughout the whole body.
Okay.
I had the opportunity
to work with Dr.
Shiwitz as a student
and then later on as a
faculty member, he would
come back to our school,
to NYT, and teach our
faculty and students for
just a cup of coffee.
He wouldn't charge us.
And one of the things
that he would echo
was Dr. Andrew
Taylor Still's saying
of find it, fix it,
and leave it alone.
Right. It really kind of
points out, you know, once
we find it and hopefully
using the AGR now, you
know where to how to find
it, fix it and then leave
it alone and let it do its
thing. And so Dr. Shiawitz
was the founder of the
OMM department at NYTCOM,
and he was treating like
50 patients a day in
Brooklyn in his private
practice, and he was recruited
to come and start the OMM
department here at NYT.
he really was already
using these concepts and
treatments but he started
teaching the OMM fellows they
didn't know what he was
doing he decided to put it
together into a paper and
a textbook and he coined it
facilitated positional
release in fact the residents
who would work with him not
the residents the fellows
who work with him initially
would just put in a
note io when he was treating
patients because they
would work on something over
and over and it wouldn't
release. It wouldn't treat.
And then he would come
in and just kind of lean
and kind of put their,
put his body weight on
somebody and just turn
them a little bit. And
then that dysfunction would
be gone. And they didn't
know what he was doing.
And so they wrote IO and
he was like, what is this
IO thing? And they're
like, oh, it's instant
osteopathy because we don't
know what you're doing.
And so he coined and put
what he was doing into the
textbook. He called it
facilitated positional release.
And so Dr. Scheiwitz
pretty much put what he
was working on with
his patients into the
textbook, and he
continued to teach us all
the different approaches
that he would use to
try to treat musculoskeletal
restrictions.
He was influenced by
earlier indirect techniques
such as strain
-counterstrain, and really
he designed this to be
efficient in the clinical
setting because he was
treating 50 patients
a day in his Brooklyn
outpatient practice.
So the key concept here is
it is an indirect technique.
The proposed mechanism is
that similar to counter
strain, you're quieting
that muscle spindle, right?
So in counter strain,
we kind of fold and hold
and we shorten the muscle.
In FPR, we're adding a
compressive force to almost
shorten it even more,
even quicker, so that that
spindle resets quicker.
than 90 seconds. So really,
for Dr. Scheiwitz, it was
instant osteopathy. But in
the textbook, he said three
to five seconds is what you
hold the compression for.
So for FPR, if you have
hypertonic muscles, you
have a semantus function,
you could treat some
contraindications. You've
got to be careful if the
patient has any acute
fractures or dislocations,
severe osteoporosis,
malignancy in the
treatment area, severe
neurodeficits, or patients
really uncomfortable
It can't tolerate
that compression.
Key thing that Dr. Shalowitz
always talked about
was that you have to
follow your finger, right?
The most important thing
is that you need to
be able to feel that
compressive force at your
monitoring finger and
you don't want to go
past it. So when you're
treating any region,
you got to place it
into a neutral position.
You're going to apply a
little bit of a facilitated
force or compression. Sometimes
it might be towards your
attraction, depending on
where you're on the body.
And then you move it
towards the position
of ease, hold it for
three to five seconds
and then return it
back to neutral. These
are the key steps and
principles, right?
And so you want
to reduce muscle
tension, improve
range of motion.
Ideally,
the more effective you
are in being localized
and precise with
your motions, the
more likely the technique
will work. Okay.
So we're going to
go over FPR and the
cervical spine, thoracic
and lumbar spine.
Again, the key thing is
monitoring with your monitoring
hand and then making
the accurate diagnosis.
If your diagnosis is
incorrect, you're going to be
putting it not into its
ideal freedoms, right? So
we're going to neutralize
the area. Here, the head
is off the table, so we're
going to provide a little
more extension, but
please, please, please be
careful when moving the
head at any time and being
careful not to hyperextend.
You really just need enough
extension to get to where
you're working. Okay?
So we're going to find the
segment, we're going to
neutralize the area, and
then we're going to apply a
compressive force to our
finger and then move it into
its freedoms. Hold it for
three to five seconds and
then reassess. For the
thoracic spine, you can perform
this seated, especially
if it's treating a flexion
dysfunction, you're going
to have to kind of treat it
seated. If it is a extension
dysfunction or superficial
muscle, you could treat
it with the patient prone.
The pillows are used
when the patients are
prone to try to neutralize
the spine. So we're
a little bit more
kyphotic. So putting a
pillow underneath the
chest could kind of
straighten that area out
to neutralize the spine.
Again, we're going to
monitor the hypertonic
muscle or the
somatic dysfunction,
add a little compressive
force through the shoulder.
And then if it's an
extension dysfunction, just
kind of lift the shoulder
up and that extends to
that segment and will also
rotate and side bend to
that side so you're going
to actually by pulling down
a little bit that creates
a side bending in a
seated position you're going
to stand on the same side
of the dysfunction
especially um yeah type two
dysfunctions you're going
to stand on the side of the
um side bending rotation
side bending stand on the
side of side bending
because then that you could
kind of lean your shoulder
here or arm to kind of
create that side bending
to the monitoring finger.
For the lumbar spine,
if we have hypertonic
muscle in the lumbar spine,
again, pillow underneath
the belly here flattens
and neutralizes,
and we're going to hold
on to the contralateral
leg here and then kind of
bring our, well, we'll just
kind of stand up and that
creates of torque here and
also twist to rotate and
shorten these muscles on this
opposite on the same you're
standing on the same side
of the hyper muscle
hypertonicity so this is the left
side of the patient it could
also be done in a seated
position but we are showing
you the more complex
prone positions here for
the lumbar spine here for an
extension semantics function
shy was put a pillow underneath
the belly and the second
one underneath the thigh
that serves as a fulcrum so
that when you um push the
leg down over that pillow
it's almost like a seesaw
and you see how that would
extend to that segment okay
and then for a flexion
dysfunction so here we're
monitoring on the same side
we're going to flex that leg
up right flexing that segment
and then we're going to
So A,
D, duct the knee, and then
internally rotate, and
that creates that motion
towards the movement by side
bending towards the freedom,
and then we're going
to add a compressive force
by bringing the hand up
the leg here, and that
creates a compression force.
So we're going to demonstrate
those and practice
those in lab.
So hopefully by screening
and approaching our
patients, utilizing the
error of grace restriction,
it gives you a approach
to treat your patients
to kind of sequence
where you should really
prioritize your treatment,
where you should start.
This is not the only best
possible screening approach.
There are many different
approaches out there,
but this is the one that
we're going to cover in lab
today. So you could really
start to figure out, hey,
where should you start
when treating your patient,
keeping the whole person
in mind, understanding
that we're a tensegrative
structure and how these
biomechanical forces will
affect our patient's health.
FPR is a great, safe,
effective treatment
that I use a lot
in my patients.
And in introducing
this to you, we hope
that this will give
you another tool in
your arsenal to help
treat your patients.
Okay, we'll see you in lab.